Okay, so this brings us to module four.
And this is the cross ecosystem contrast comparison
where we are looking at our different data,
lung data sets related from HubMap,
the single nucleates that we then process
into the pseudobulk for this comparison,
as well as the GTECS bulk values
that we specifically have been,
so that you have your appropriate age comparison,
and then the geofibrosis cohort,
as well as the NASA space flight study for mouse.
So, you know, and there's somebody asked like,
why space flight?
So the reason space flight is here
is a comparison about aging and disease
and it's not necessarily arbitrary.
So microgravity and space radiation
are studied explicitly as a model of accelerated aging,
producing the inflammation, senescence
and fibrotic remodeling signatures
that characterize age tissue
and even a genomic radiation age association
has directly been carried into lung diseases.
So this is why it's important for,
just as an exploratory analysis for this cross ecosystem
to compare the different age contrasts,
specifically to the fibrosis cohort
as well as the space flight.
So how do you do that?
So you have different platforms, different units,
different species even, so different processing.
And this model really talks about the best way to do that
is to look at what actually does travel.
And it's the contrast.
So within each resource you've computed under one design,
you have the log-to-fold change,
and then the pathway enrichment score.
So really the normalized enrichment score
is going to be what we use to be able to find
concordance between the different data sets
and the relevant biological mechanisms.
So, you know, following again a similar template
as the previous modules,
looking at our method section.
We have six steps.
So we have the four within resource contrast,
one, differential expressed path,
and explicit reference levels.
And so all of this to be able to integrate
at the pathway normalize enrichment score,
and then looked at the share mechanism
concordance across those different data sets.
So following the same structure, again,
we go through the calibration of the space flight.
So this is important.
So we looked at specific X-fold spike and calibration
to ensure that there's legitimacy to the--
there's not any sort of ERCC confounding data problems
or whatsoever.
So that was ran and was successful.
So then we-- important here, critical to address
is the ortholog mapping.
So we are able to then map the mouse to human tissue
because again, the NAS-OSDR data is wrote in research data
and needs to be mapped for proper comparison.
And then it goes into the pathway enrichment values.
So we then look at some of our results where, first,
you're going to look at some of the differential
express genes across the different conditions.
And then it brings us into concordance.
So we're looking at here aging versus disease
and looking at what has showed positive correlation
between the two modalities and some of the,
or sorry, the two different experiments
and then what are some of the most important
biological takeaways from this
And are any of these actually statistically significant,
or is it more exploratory now?
So you see, all of that is addressed throughout this
module.
So that brings us to the final section,
where it's like, how do you read this?
So then it talks about, again, the different comparisons
between the disease aging and the flight pairs,
as well as the different aging data set
compared to flight.
And some different ways that you could potentially
extend the analysis.
And I think that there's a lot of things here
that could be further discussed.
I think in increasing your core size,
maybe potentially integrating additional data sets
for the space data, could be relevant.
There's a couple different studies out there
that also deal with lung tissue.
And then if there's any sort of human orthologs or human data,
rather, that would be most applicable,
maybe that would be important to consider.
So this brings us to kind of the end of the cross ecosystem
looking at the pathway concordance across the different data
sets.
And really, this will be the last screencast.
So I just also want to bring the attention to module 5,
which is the assessment module for this entire learning program.
And everything that you watched produce results
and raise it over states.
Module five really is a 30 minutes of tuning
of the computational results into what actually
is going to be defendable.
So you're looking at--
you spend 10 minutes of the show on just a knowledge check
looking at different considerations across the modules
one through four.
And then at the end, the second part is a 20 minute--
it would take approximately 20 minutes.
It might take more.
But to write an abstract that would apply--
where you apply this approach to a question of your own.
So the goal here is to really take everything
that you learned from this module or these different modules
and the CFD resources and organize it into some sort of a hypothetical research campaign
of your own and then, you know, it's on you to follow through with it as needed.
So I hope you enjoyed the learning objectives and I hope you, yeah, were able to take some
of the key interesting considerations away related to understanding how to interpret
transcriptomic data related to lung tissue.